My colleagues and I are fascinated by the science of moving dots.
زملائي و انا معجبين بعلم النقاط المتحركة
So what are these dots?
فما هي هذه النقاط ؟
Well, it's all of us.
حسنا، هي كل واحد منا.
And we're moving in our homes, in our offices, as we shop and travel
و نحن نتحرك في بيوتنا، في مكاتبنا، كما نحن نتسوق و نسافر
throughout our cities and around the world.
خلال مدننا و حول العالم.
And wouldn't it be great if we could understand all this movement?
اليس من الجيد من ان نكون قادرين على ان نتفهم كل هذه التحركات
If we could find patterns and meaning and insight in it.
اذا كنا قادرين على ايجاد انماط و معاني و النظر في ذلك
And luckily for us, we live in a time
و لحسن الحظ لنا، نحن نعيش في زمان
where we're incredibly good at capturing information about ourselves.
و نحن بشكل لا يصدق جيدين في التقاط معلومات عن انفسنا
So whether it's through sensors or videos, or apps,
و ذلك سواء من خلال اجهزة الاستشعار او الفيديو, او التطبيقات
we can track our movement with incredibly fine detail.
نحن نستطيع تتبع حركاتنا بتفاصيل دقيقة لا تصدق
So it turns out one of the places where we have the best data about movement
لذلك تبين ان احد الاماكن حيث وجدنا ان افضل بيانات حول الحركة
is sports.
هي الرياضة
So whether it's basketball or baseball, or football or the other football,
ذلك سواء اكان في كرة السلة او البيسبول, او كرة القدم او كرة القدم الاخرى
we're instrumenting our stadiums and our players to track their movements
نحن نجهز ملاعبنا بالاجهزة و لاعبينا حتى نتتبع حركاتهم
every fraction of a second.
كل جزء من الثانية
So what we're doing is turning our athletes into --
و ما نفعله هو تحويل لاعبينا الى
you probably guessed it --
ربما عرفتم الى ماذا
moving dots.
نقاط متحركة
So we've got mountains of moving dots and like most raw data,
لذلك لدينا كومة من النقاط المتحركة و كمعظم البينات الاولية،
it's hard to deal with and not that interesting.
من الصعب التعامل معها و ليس بتلك المتعة.
But there are things that, for example, basketball coaches want to know.
لكن هناك اشياء التي على سبيل المثال، مدربين كرة السلة يريدون معرفته.
And the problem is they can't know them because they'd have to watch every second
و المشكلة انه لا يمكنهم معرفتها لانهم بحاجة الى مشاهدة كل ثانية
of every game, remember it and process it.
من كل مباراة، تذكره و معالجته.
And a person can't do that,
و الانسان لا يمكنه فعل ذلك
but a machine can.
لكن الآلة تستطيع
The problem is a machine can't see the game with the eye of a coach.
المشكلة ان الآلة لا تسطيع ان ترى المباراة كما يراها المدرب
At least they couldn't until now.
على الاقل لم يتمكنوا حتى اﻷن
So what have we taught the machine to see?
فماذا علمنا الآلة ان ترى؟
So, we started simply.
لذلك بدأنا ببساطة.
We taught it things like passes, shots and rebounds.
علمناها اشياء مثل التمريرات، و لقطات و الترددات.
Things that most casual fans would know.
اشياء التي يعرفها المشجعين العاديين.
And then we moved on to things slightly more complicated.
و من ثم انتقلنا الى الاشياء الاكثر تعقيدا بقليل.
Events like post-ups, and pick-and-rolls, and isolations.
احداث مثل "بوست ابس" و انتقاء و لفات, و العزلة
And if you don't know them, that's okay. Most casual players probably do.
و اذا لم تعرفوهم, لا بأس بذلك. معظم اللاعبين العاديين ربما يعرفون.
Now, we've gotten to a point where today, the machine understands complex events
الان, نحن وصلنا الى نقطة حيث ان اليوم, الآلة تفهم احداث معقدة
like down screens and wide pins.
مثل "داون سكرينس" و "وايد بينس"
Basically things only professionals know.
الاشياء التي يعرفها المحترفين اساسا.
So we have taught a machine to see with the eyes of a coach.
لذلك علمنا اﻵلة بان ترى كما يرى المدرب .
So how have we been able to do this?
فكيف كنا قادرين على فعل ذلك؟
If I asked a coach to describe something like a pick-and-roll,
اذا سألت مدرب بأن يصف لي شيئا مثل "بيك-اند-رول",
they would give me a description,
لاعطوني وصف،
and if I encoded that as an algorithm, it would be terrible.
و لو شفرت ذلك كخوارزمية، سيكون فظيعا.
The pick-and-roll happens to be this dance in basketball between four players,
ال"بيك-اند-رول" حدث ان تكون هذه الرقصة في كرة السلة بين اربعة لاعبين,
two on offense and two on defense.
اثنين على الهجوم و اثنين علي الدفاع.
And here's kind of how it goes.
وهنا نوعا ما كيف تسير الأمور.
So there's the guy on offense without the ball
اذا هنالك الشخص على الموقع الهجومي دون الكرة
the ball and he goes next to the guy guarding the guy with the ball,
هو و الكرة يذهبان الى جانب الشخص الذي يحرس الشخص مع الكرة،
and he kind of stays there
و هو نوعا ما يبقى هناك
and they both move and stuff happens, and ta-da, it's a pick-and-roll.
و كلاهما يتحركان و اشياء تحدث, و تا-دا, انها "بيك-اند-رول".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So that is also an example of a terrible algorithm.
اذا هذا ايضا مثال على خوارزمية فظيعة.
So, if the player who's the interferer -- he's called the screener --
اذا, اذا كان اللاعب الذي يتدخل -- هو يسمي ب"سكرينير"--
goes close by, but he doesn't stop,
يذهب بالقرب من, لكنه لا يتوقف،
it's probably not a pick-and-roll.
انها لربما ليست " بيك-اند-رول".
Or if he does stop, but he doesn't stop close enough,
او اذا توقف, لكنه لا يتوقف لا يقترب الى حد كافي,
it's probably not a pick-and-roll.
انها لربما ليست " بيك-اند-رول".
Or, if he does go close by and he does stop
او, اذا اقترب منه و هو يتوقف
but they do it under the basket, it's probably not a pick-and-roll.
لكنهم يفعلوها تحت السلة, انها لربما ليست " بيك-اند-رول".
Or I could be wrong, they could all be pick-and-rolls.
او قد اكون مخطئ, من الممكن ان كلهن " بيك-اند-رول".
It really depends on the exact timing, the distances, the locations,
و هو حقا على يعتمد على الوقت الدقيق و المسافات و المواقع
and that's what makes it hard.
و هذا ما يجعله صعب.
So, luckily, with machine learning, we can go beyond our own ability
لذلك مع حسن الحظ، مع تعلم الآلة، يمكننا تجاوز قدراتنا
to describe the things we know.
لوصف الاشياء التي نعرفها.
So how does this work? Well, it's by example.
فكيف هذا يعمل؟ حسنا انها من خلال النماذج.
So we go to the machine and say, "Good morning, machine.
لذلك نحن الى الآلة و نقول, " صباح الخير يا آلة.
Here are some pick-and-rolls, and here are some things that are not.
و ها هنا بعض "بيك اند رولس", و ها هنا بعض الاشياء التي ليست.
Please find a way to tell the difference."
من فضلك جد طريقة لمعرفة الفرق."
And the key to all of this is to find features that enable it to separate.
و المفتاح لكل هذا هو ايجاد المميزات التي تمكنها من الفصل.
So if I was going to teach it the difference
لذلك اذا كنت ذاهبا لاعلمها الفروق
between an apple and orange,
بين تفاحة و البرتقال
I might say, "Why don't you use color or shape?"
ربما اقول, "لماذا لا تستخدم لون او شكل؟"
And the problem that we're solving is, what are those things?
و المشكلة التي نحلها هي، ما هي هذه الاشياء؟
What are the key features
ما هي الملامح الرئيسية
that let a computer navigate the world of moving dots?
التي تدع الكمبيوتر التنقل في عالم النقاط المتحركة؟
So figuring out all these relationships with relative and absolute location,
لذلك اكتشاف كل هذه العلاقات مع موقع النسبي و المطلق،
distance, timing, velocities --
مسافة، التوقيت، سرعات--
that's really the key to the science of moving dots, or as we like to call it,
هذا هو حقا المفتاح علم النقاط المتحركة او كما نحب ان نسميه،
spatiotemporal pattern recognition, in academic vernacular.
التعرف على الانماط الزمانية المكانية، في الاكادمية العامية.
Because the first thing is, you have to make it sound hard --
لان اول شئ هو، يجب عليك ان تجعل الامر يبدو صعب--
because it is.
لانه كذلك.
The key thing is, for NBA coaches, it's not that they want to know
الشيئ الرئيسي لمدربين NBA هو ليس انهم لا يريدون معرفة
whether a pick-and-roll happened or not.
اذا حدث "بيك اند رول" ام لم يحدث.
It's that they want to know how it happened.
هو انهم يريدون معرفة كيف حدث.
And why is it so important to them? So here's a little insight.
و لماذا هذا مهم لهم؟ اذا هذه معرفة بسيطة.
It turns out in modern basketball,
اتضح ان في كرة السلة الحديثة,
this pick-and-roll is perhaps the most important play.
ربما ال"بيك اند رول" اهم اللعب.
And knowing how to run it, and knowing how to defend it,
و معرفة كيفية ادارتها, و معرفة كيفية حمايتها,
is basically a key to winning and losing most games.
هو اساسا مفتاح الفوز و الخسارة في معظم المباريات.
So it turns out that this dance has a great many variations
اتضح ان هذه الرقصة لها عدد كبير من البدائل
and identifying the variations is really the thing that matters,
و تعريف هذه البدائل هو الامر المهم,
and that's why we need this to be really, really good.
و لهذا لماذا نحن نحتاج من ان ذلك يكون جيد جدا,
So, here's an example.
اذن, هذا مثال.
There are two offensive and two defensive players,
هنلك لاعبين اثنين مهاجمين و لاعبين اثنين مدافعين,
getting ready to do the pick-and-roll dance.
مستدعين ليقوموا رقصة ال"بيك اند رول".
So the guy with ball can either take, or he can reject.
اذن الشخص مع الكرة يمكنه يأخذ او يمكنه يرفض
His teammate can either roll or pop.
بامكان زملائه اما ان يفعلو ال"رول" او "بوب".
The guy guarding the ball can either go over or under.
الشخص الذي يحرس الكرة يمكنه اما ان يذهب من فوق او من تحت.
His teammate can either show or play up to touch, or play soft
زملائه يمكنهم اما الاظهار او اللعب حتى اللمس او اللعب بليونه
and together they can either switch or blitz
و مع بعضهم اما يمكنهم التبديل او الهجوم
and I didn't know most of these things when I started
و لم أعرف معظم هذه الاشياء عندما بدأت
and it would be lovely if everybody moved according to those arrows.
وسيكون من الرائع لو ان الجميع تحركوا وفقا لهذه الاسهم.
It would make our lives a lot easier, but it turns out movement is very messy.
سيجعل حياتنا اسهل بكثير, و لكن اتضح ان الحركات فوضوية جدا.
People wiggle a lot and getting these variations identified
الناس يهتزون كثيرا و تعريف هذه المتغيرات
with very high accuracy,
مع الدقة العالية,
both in precision and recall, is tough
في كلا الدقة و الاسترداد صعب
because that's what it takes to get a professional coach to believe in you.
لان هذا ما يلزم لمدرب المحترف يصدقك.
And despite all the difficulties with the right spatiotemporal features
و بالرغم من الصعوبات المتعلقة بالملامح الزمانية و المكانية الصحيحة
we have been able to do that.
استطعنا القيام من ذلك.
Coaches trust our ability of our machine to identify these variations.
المدربين يؤمنون بقدرات آلتنا في تحديد هذه المتغيرات.
We're at the point where almost every single contender
نحن عند النقطة حيث ان كل منافس تقريبا
for an NBA championship this year
لبطولة الNBA في هذا العام
is using our software, which is built on a machine that understands
يستخدم برمجياتنا المبنية على الآلة التي تدرك
the moving dots of basketball.
النقاط المتحركة لكرة السلة.
So not only that, we have given advice that has changed strategies
و ليس فقط ذلك، بل واعطينا النصائح التي غيرت استراتيجيات
that have helped teams win very important games,
التي ساعدت الفرق في الفوز في مباريات مهمة،
and it's very exciting because you have coaches who've been in the league
و هذا في غاية الاثارة لان لديك مدربين الذين كانوا في الدوري
for 30 years that are willing to take advice from a machine.
لمدة 30 عاما الذين هم مستعدين ﻹخذ نصائح من آلة.
And it's very exciting, it's much more than the pick-and-roll.
و هو مثير جدا، و اكثر بكثير من "بيك اند رول".
Our computer started out with simple things
حاسوبنا ابتدأ بالاشياء الصغيرة
and learned more and more complex things
و تعلم المزيد و المجزيد من الاشياء المعقدة
and now it knows so many things.
و الان يعرف اشياء كثيرة.
Frankly, I don't understand much of what it does,
بصراحة، انا لا افهم كثيرا بما يفعله
and while it's not that special to be smarter than me,
و حينما انه ليس من المهم ان يكون اذكى مني،
we were wondering, can a machine know more than a coach?
نحن كن نتسائل هل يمكن للآلة ان تعرف اكثر من المدرب؟
Can it know more than person could know?
هل يمكنها ان تعرف اكثر من الشخص؟
And it turns out the answer is yes.
و اتضح ان الجواب هو نعم.
The coaches want players to take good shots.
المدربين يريدون اللاعبين لاتخاذ ضربات جيدة.
So if I'm standing near the basket
لذلك اذا كنت وواقفا بجانب السلة
and there's nobody near me, it's a good shot.
و ليس هناك احد بجانبي، انها ضربة جيدة.
If I'm standing far away surrounded by defenders, that's generally a bad shot.
اذا كنت واقفا بعيدا و محاصر بالمدافعين ، تلك بشكل عام ضربة سيئة.
But we never knew how good "good" was, or how bad "bad" was quantitatively.
و لكننا لم نعرف كيف الجيد كان "جيدا" او كيف السيئ كان "سيئا" كميا.
Until now.
حتى الان.
So what we can do, again, using spatiotemporal features,
اذا ما يمكننا فعله، مجددا، هو استخدام ميزات الزمانية و المكانية،
we looked at every shot.
نظرنا الى لقطة.
We can see: Where is the shot? What's the angle to the basket?
بامكاننا ان نرى: اين اللقطة؟ أي زاوية الى السلة؟
Where are the defenders standing? What are their distances?
اين المهاجمون واقفون؟ ما هي مسافاتهم؟
What are their angles?
ما هي زواياهم؟
For multiple defenders, we can look at how the player's moving
لعدة مهاجمين، يمكننا ان نرى كيف يتحرك اللاعبون
and predict the shot type.
و تنبؤ نوعية المحاولة.
We can look at all their velocities and we can build a model that predicts
يمكننا ان نرى جميع سرعاتهم و يمكننا ان نبنى نموذج الذي يتوقع
what is the likelihood that this shot would go in under these circumstances?
ما هو الاحتمال ان المحاولة ستسير وفق هذه الظروف؟
So why is this important?
اذن لماذا هذا مهم؟
We can take something that was shooting,
يمكننا اخذ شيئ كان يرمي،
which was one thing before, and turn it into two things:
الذي كان شيئ واحد من قبل و تحويله الى شيئين:
the quality of the shot and the quality of the shooter.
نوعية الرمية و نوعية الرامي.
So here's a bubble chart, because what's TED without a bubble chart?
اذن هذا تخطيط فقاعي، لأنه ما هو TED من دون تخطيط فقاعي؟
(Laughter)
( ضحك)
Those are NBA players.
هؤلاء لاعبين NBA
The size is the size of the player and the color is the position.
الحجم هو حجم اللاعب و اللون هو الموقع.
On the x-axis, we have the shot probability.
على محور السيني لدينا احتمالات الرمية.
People on the left take difficult shots,
الاشخاص على اليسار يتخذون رميات صعبة،
on the right, they take easy shots.
على اليمين، يتخذون رميات سهلة.
On the [y-axis] is their shooting ability.
على محور الصادي هي قدراتهم على الرماية.
People who are good are at the top, bad at the bottom.
الاشخاص الجيدين في الاعلى، السيئين في الاسفل.
So for example, if there was a player
اذن على سبيل المثال، اذا كان هناك لاعب
who generally made 47 percent of their shots,
الذي عموما جعل 47 بالمئة من الرميات،
that's all you knew before.
هذا كل ما عرفتوه مسبقا.
But today, I can tell you that player takes shots that an average NBA player
لكن اليوم، يمكنني ان اقول لكم ان اللاعب الذي يتخذ رميات ان لاعب الNBA العادي
would make 49 percent of the time,
يمكنه النجاح 49 بالمئة من الوقت،
and they are two percent worse.
و هم 2 بالمئة اسوأ.
And the reason that's important is that there are lots of 47s out there.
و سبب اهميته لأن هناك كثيرين بهذا المستوى .
And so it's really important to know
و هذا امر مهم لمعرفته
if the 47 that you're considering giving 100 million dollars to
اذا قررت اعطائهم 100 مليون دولار
is a good shooter who takes bad shots
من يرمي جيدا و يتخذ رميات جيد
or a bad shooter who takes good shots.
او من يرمي بسوء و يتخذ رميات جيدة.
Machine understanding doesn't just change how we look at players,
فهم الآلة ليس فقط تغير كيف ننظر الى اللاعبين،
it changes how we look at the game.
انها تغير نظرتنا الى المباراة.
So there was this very exciting game a couple of years ago, in the NBA finals.
كانت هناك مباراة ممتعة جدا قبل بضعة سنين، في نهائيات الNBA.
Miami was down by three, there was 20 seconds left.
كانت ميامي اقل بثلاث نقاط، و تبقى من 20 ثانية.
They were about to lose the championship.
كانوا على وشك خسارة البطولة.
A gentleman named LeBron James came up and he took a three to tie.
جاء رجل اسمه لابرون جيمس و اتخذ ثلاث للتعادل.
He missed.
لكنه اخفق.
His teammate Chris Bosh got a rebound,
زميله كريس حصل على ارتداد،
passed it to another teammate named Ray Allen.
مرره الى زميله الاخر اسمه راي الان.
He sank a three. It went into overtime.
و اغرق ثلاث. فاتوا بالوقت الاضافي.
They won the game. They won the championship.
فازوا المباراة. فازوا البطولة.
It was one of the most exciting games in basketball.
كانت احد المباريات المثيرة جدا في كرة السلة.
And our ability to know the shot probability for every player
و قدرتنا علي معرفة احتمالات محاولات لكل لاعب
at every second,
في كل ثانية،
and the likelihood of them getting a rebound at every second
و احتمال حصولهم على ارتداد في كل ثانية
can illuminate this moment in a way that we never could before.
يمكنه توضيح اللحظة بطريقة لم نستطع بها من قبل.
Now unfortunately, I can't show you that video.
اﻵن للاسف، لا يمكنني ان اريكم ذلك الفيديو.
But for you, we recreated that moment
لكن لكم، نحن صوغنا تلك اللحظة
at our weekly basketball game about 3 weeks ago.
في مبارتنا لكرة السلة قبل حوالي ثلاثة اسابيع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
And we recreated the tracking that led to the insights.
و صوغنا التتابع الذي الى ادى المشاهد.
So, here is us. This is Chinatown in Los Angeles,
اذن، ها هنا نحن. هذا الحي الصيني في لوس انجلوس،
a park we play at every week,
منتزه نلعب فيه كل اسبوع،
and that's us recreating the Ray Allen moment
و ها نحن نصوغ لحظة راي الان
and all the tracking that's associated with it.
و كل التتابع المرتبط بتلك باللحظة.
So, here's the shot.
اذن، هذه هي الرمية.
I'm going to show you that moment
سوف اريكم تلك اللحظة
and all the insights of that moment.
و كل المشاهد من تلك اللحظة.
The only difference is, instead of the professional players, it's us,
الاختلاف الوحيد هو، انه نحن بدلا من لاعبين محترفين،
and instead of a professional announcer, it's me.
و انا بدلا من معلّق محترف، انا المعلّق.
So, bear with me.
اذن، تحملوا معي.
Miami.
ميامي
Down three.
خاسرين بثلاث نقاط.
Twenty seconds left.
عشرون ثانية باقية.
Jeff brings up the ball.
جيف يحضر الكرة.
Josh catches, puts up a three!
جوش يلتقطها، و يسدد بثلاث نقاط!
[Calculating shot probability]
[حساب احتمالات الرمية]
[Shot quality]
[جودة الرمية ]
[Rebound probability]
[ احتمال الارتداد]
Won't go!
لن يحدث!
Rebound, Noel.
ارتداد، نويل.
Back to Daria.
نرجع الى داريا.
[Shot quality]
[ جودة الرمية ]
Her three-pointer -- bang!
رميتها الثلاثية --بانج!
Tie game with five seconds left.
تعادل المباراة مع خمسة ثواني متبقيات.
The crowd goes wild.
الجمهور يقفز.
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
That's roughly how it happened.
و هذا تقريبا كيف حدث.
(Applause)
( تصفيق )
Roughly.
تقريبا.
That moment had about a nine percent chance of happening in the NBA
كانت فرصة حدوث تلك الحظة حوالي 9 بالمئة في NBA
and we know that and a great many other things.
و نحن نعرف ذلك و أشياء كثيرة عظيمة اخرى.
I'm not going to tell you how many times it took us to make that happen.
لن اقول لكم كم مرة استغرقنا من تحقيق ذلك.
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Okay, I will! It was four.
حسنا، سوف اقول! اربعة مرات.
Way to go, Daria.
احسنت يا داريا.
But the important thing about that video
لكن الامر المهم عن ذلك الفيديو
and the insights we have for every second of every NBA game -- it's not that.
و رؤيات التي لدينا لكل ثانية لكل لعبة NBA -- ليس ذلك.
It's the fact you don't have to be a professional team to track movement.
هي الحقيقة انه ليس من الضروري ان تكون فريقا محترفا لتتابع الحركات.
You do not have to be a professional player to get insights about movement.
ليس من الضروري ان تكون لاعبا محترفا للحصول على رؤيات الحركات.
In fact, it doesn't even have to be about sports because we're moving everywhere.
في الحقيقة، ليس من الضروري من ان تكون عن الرياضة لانه نحن نتحرك في كل مكان.
We're moving in our homes,
نحن نتحرك في بيوتنا،
in our offices,
في مكاتبنا،
as we shop and we travel
كما نحن نتسوق و نسافر
throughout our cities
عبر مدننا
and around our world.
و حول العالم.
What will we know? What will we learn?
ما الذي سنعرفه؟ ما الذي سنتعلمه؟
Perhaps, instead of identifying pick-and-rolls,
ربكا بدلا من تعريف "بيك اند رولز"،
a machine can identify the moment and let me know
اﻵلة يمكنها ان تعرف اللحظة و تعلمني بها
when my daughter takes her first steps.
عندما تتخطى ابنتي خطواتها الاولى.
Which could literally be happening any second now.
التي يمكن ان تحدث في اي لحظة.
Perhaps we can learn to better use our buildings, better plan our cities.
ربما يمكننا التعلم لاستخدام افضل لمبانينا، تخطيط افضل لمدننا.
I believe that with the development of the science of moving dots,
انا اؤمن ان مع تطور علم النقاط المتحركة،
we will move better, we will move smarter, we will move forward.
سوف نتحرك افضل، سوف نتحرك بذكاء، سوف نتحرك للامام.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
( تصفيق)